A Guide to the Papers of John Fiske 1872-1900
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Fiske, 1872-1900
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7192-a
This collection consists of 27 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Clifton Waller Barrett on July 1, 1964.
Scope and Content Information
Letters are chiefly concerned with Fiske's writing and publication, textual revisions, lecturing, and book reviewing. Specific works of his mentioned include: Cosmic Philosophy, Discovery of America, and Unseen World.
Fiske provides information about Governor John Culpeper; refers to restraints in his Houghton-Mifflin contract; and discusses Spinoza, mentioning books about him by James Martineau and Frederick Pollock.
Correspondents include Francis Jackson Garrison, J.B. Greenough, Wendell Phillips Garrison, S.S. McClure, George Pellew, Thomas Sergeant, William Henry Rideing, Charles Dudley Warner, J.G. Wilson, N.J. Bartlett & Co., and J.B. Millet Co.
The collection also contains photographs, autographs, personal checks and a Harvard library form.
Contents List
- Letters
  - John Fiske to Rev. A. Blaewell 1872 Mar 31, ALS, 1 p.
    Refers to his article on Jesus for the World, to the Modern Thinker, and to his revision of the Cosmic Philosophy. Notes the decided antagonism to Positivism.
  - J. F. to [Thomas Sergeant ?] Perry 1881 Mar 29, ALS, 1 p.
    Note written in mock Biblical style, with "Perry" transliterated in Greek characters, and a musical notation substituted for word "see." Encourages Perry in an unspecified conflict.
  - J. F. to the Rev. A. J. Sullivan 1886 Jan 23, ALS, 2 p.
    Mentions Prof. Smyth's articles in Andover Rev[iew]. Refers to Martineau's A Study of Spinonza(1882) and to Frederick Pollack's Spinoza--His Life and Philosophy(1880). Mentions his work on a history of the American people.
  - J. F. to [George] Pellew 1886 Dec 8, ALS, 1 p.
    Invites him to look over ms. along with "T. S. P."
  - J. F. to [William Henry] Rideing 1887 Aug 1, ALS, 1 p.
    Sends six copies for articles relating to Revoluntionary War. Discusses price. Mentions $40 per article.
  - J. F. to W. H. R. 1887 Aug 18, ALS, 1 p.
    Inquires after articles sent.
  - J. F. to [James Grant?] Wilson 1887 Sep 25, ALS, 3 p.
    Has mailed proofs of [Thomas Jefferson] Jackson, Lafayette, and Lee articles. Discusses work on Lees and Madison. Mentions O. B. Frothingham.
  - J. F. to F. J. Garrison 1891 Oct 12, ALS, 4 p.
    Discusses his writing, including Discovery of America.
  - J. F. to F. J. Garrison 1894 Feb 10, ALS, 2 p.
    Needs to get facts on woman's suffrage, to make corrections to a new edition of a book on [civil government?].
  - J. F. to Charles Dudley Warner 1894 Feb 20, ALS, 4 p., w/ env.
    Expresses interest in Parkman project. Thought Warner was Lester Ward, author of Dynamic Sociology.
  - J. F. to J. B. Millet Co. 1895 Oct 5, ALS, 1 p.
    Concerns changes in his copy of Famous Composers.
  - J. F. to Mr. Addison 1895 Oct 7, ALS, 1 p.
    Accepts dinner invitation.
  - J. F. to John 1896 Mar 29, ALS, 1 p.
    Admiration of John
  - J. F. to Mr. Riddle 1879 Jul 14, ALS, 1 p.
    Appreciates letter in praise of his work.
  - J. F. to Miss Wilkins 1900 Mar 31, ALS, 2 p.
    Provides biographical information on Governor John Culpeper; mentions Appleton's Cyclopaedia of American Biography, Stephen's Dictionary of National Biography, and Doyle's Peerage. Mentions Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - J. F. to L. A. Whittier 1891 Sep 4, APCS, 1 p.
    Discusses textual revisions of unidentified work being printed by the Riverside Press.
  - J. F. to Samuel Sidney McClure 1892 Sep 24, APCS, 1 p.
    Contract to Houghton-Mifflin Co. precludes his writing for another.
  - J. F. to Samuel Sidney McClure 1894 Feb 19, APCS, 1 p.
    Cannot write for magazines unless owned by Houghton-Mifflin.
  - J.F. to [printers?] n.d., ANS, n.d.
    Explains his proof-reading marks.
- Miscellaneous
  - "Very truly yrs" n.d., Autograph
  - "Sincerely yours" n.d., Autograph
  - J. F. to 1890 Mar 3, Quotation, 1 p.
    From The American Revolution, vol. ii, p. 84. W/ print of Jospeh Brant-Thayendanegea, engraved by A. Dick, from a painting by G. Romney.
  - Receipt for gift to Harvard 1877 Oct 3, Library form
    from Francis C. Lowell, signed by J. F., Assistant Librarian.
  - $10 check from J. F. to Harold F. Fiske 1889 Oct 1, Check
    on the Charles River National Bank
  - $20 check for cash by J. F. 1987 Dec 28, Check
    on the Cambridge Safe Deposit and Trust Co.
  - $10 check by J. F. to W. H. Lucas, on the Cambridge Safe Deposit and Trust Co. 1899 Feb 13, Check
- Prints
  - J. F., head and shoulders n.d., Engraving
    [Signed]